Today's דף Daf is ל"ה Lamed Hey 35 and we pick up
actually at the top of ל"ה. Lamed Hey. Let me review what
we said yesterday, we said I think we were a little bit
rushed at the end and I wanted to clarify a point. The
משנה Mishna says we went from like halachic sort of barriers to
getting to the עירוב Eiruv to physical ones, or they might also
be halachic ones as we'll see, and it says that if you
put an עירוב Eiruv in a מגדל, Migdal, which here means like
a wardrobe is how I'm describing it, is
like a certain type of a wooden chest is normally what it
is, and you don't have the key, then the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says it's fine and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's not
good.
So what is that about? So the גמרא Gemara want to know
why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's good, I mean if you
don't have the key what's the story, how can you get to
it on שבת, Shabbos, presumably you can't break it although we'll talk
about that in a minute, so first it made a special case
that it was something made out of לביני Liveini bricks without cement
where according to one position it actually is not a violation to
undo that structure of bricks. But then the גמרא Gemara got
challenged because that position even that position was only on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, so the גמרא Gemara tried to say fine the case
of the משנה Mishna is talking about יום טוב. Yom Tov. That
was answer number one. Now within that the גמרא Gemara quoted another
issue, another ברייתא Braisa of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that said that
it matters where the key was lost, that even when רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says it's no good, it's no good assuming there's not
a possibility you might be able to find the key and open
it, but if there is a possibility you could find the key
and open it you're okay. So you don't have to actually have
found the key, there just has to be that possibility. So what
would that scenario be? If it was lost in the city and
then assuming that there were a lot of רשות היחידs Reshus Hayachid
and somehow all those רשות היחידs Reshus Hayachid can get you out
to where your עירוב Eiruv is, you know then in theory were
you to find the key you could get it to where your
עירוב Eiruv was and you're okay, but if it's lost out in
the שדה Sadeh then there's no way even if you found it
so it's not good. So that basically, the חידוש Chidush there is,
well first of all the גמרא Gemara says that makes it clear
we're talking about שבת Shabbos not יום טוב Yom Tov because there's
an issue of carrying, but the חידוש Chidush there also is that
even if you didn't find the key just the ability to find
the key for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would change the story. So
if there's not possible, if the key is like completely lost, you
know whatever there's no chance you'll find it, or it's lost in
the שדה, Sadeh, then that's where רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's
a problem, but if there's a good possibility you could find the
key and get it there it's okay. Now I wanted to mention
something because the ברייתא, Braisa, the second ברייתא Braisa said, or the
way the גמרא Gemara interpreted the ברייתא, Braisa, rather than saying where
was it lost said where did you find it. Did you find
it in the city? Did you find it in the שדה? Sadeh?
And רש"י Rashi says you found it on שבת, Shabbos, presumably because
if you found it before שבת Shabbos that wouldn't be the scenario
that שבת Shabbos began and you didn't have the key, which is
the scenario. So the question is who cares if you found it
on שבת? Shabbos?
You know an עירוב Eiruv is defined by what happens when שבת
Shabbos begins. And I look to see the
ראשונים, Rishonim, they really don't discuss it but I think they're assuming
that the only point about describing when you found it is because
that shows where you lost it. Meaning if you found it in
the city then that shows that on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos it
was lost in the city, and if you found it in the
שדה Sadeh then that shows that on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos it
was lost in the שדה. Sadeh. But the גמרא, Gemara, but they
basically downplay the point about you need to find it and they
basically assume that it is as the first ברייתא Braisa discussed for
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the question about where you lost it and
that defined by the status when שבת Shabbos begins. So let's take
a look, let's just further finish that up in the גמרא Gemara
and then I'll take the question. So if you look here on
ל"ה ע"א Lamed Hey Amud Aleph we pick up with, let's
you know what let's start from the very first line of ל"ה
ע"א Lamed Hey Amud Aleph and review that. והכי קתני, v'hachi katani,
so this is how to read this ברייתא Braisa that we quoted
yesterday.
נתנו במגדל nasnu b'migdal and lost before it the מפתח. maftayeach. הרי
זה עירוב harei zeh eiruv it's good. Now that
is the חכמים, Chachamim, במה דברים אמורים b'meh devarim amurim now
when is this true that it's good? ביום טוב b'Yom Tov
that's good on יום טוב Yom Tov because on יום טוב Yom
Tov wherever you find the key, now of course who's to say
that you'll be able to find it, but if you were to
find the key you could get it and therefore get access. אבל
בשבת aval b'Shabbos אין עירובו עירוב ein eiruvo eiruv but on שבת
Shabbos it would not be good. נמצא המפתח nimtzah hamaftayeach if it
was found בין בעיר בין בשדה bein ba'ir bein basadeh אין עירובו
עירוב ein eiruvo eiruv
whether in the field or whether in the city it would not
be good. So according to this ברייתא Braisa as opposed to our
משנה Mishna where the חכמים Chachamim say flat out הרי זה עירוב
harei zeh eiruv it's good, so one minute,
right, according to
this
according to our משנה Mishna where it says flat out that it
is good, this ברייתא Braisa has the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma saying
that fundamentally it's not good
unless you know it's יום טוב Yom Tov and then if you
found it you could get to it. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer
omer and here רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer makes a
distinction, אם עירוב בעיר im eiruv ba'ir עירובו עירוב. eiruvo eiruv. Did
I skip a line? Rabbi, no, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer,
בעיר עירוב ועירוב. ba-ir eruv v'eruv. If you found it in the
city, which means it was lost in the city, then it is
good because then you could have gotten it to the, you could
have gotten it to the wardrobe. בשדה, Basadeh, if it was found
in the field, which therefore means it was lost in the field,
אין עירוב ועירוב, ein eruv v'eruv, it's not good because therefore there
was no way to have gotten it there when שבת Shabbos began.
Now we're going to explain that. בעיר עירוב ועירוב כרבי שמעון. Ba-ir
eruv v'eruv k'Rabbi Shimon.
In the city, you know, it's good like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
דאמר אחד גגות ואחד חצרות ואחד קרפיפות רשות אחת הן לכלים ששבתו
בתוכן. d'amar echad gaggot v'echad chatzerot v'echad karpifot reshut achat hen l'kelim
sheshavtu b'tochan. And this is what I just said at the end
of yesterday, that even though the way to get it to the
עירוב eruv would require going from one רשות היחיד reshut hayachid to
another and they would be different types of רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid,
you might have to take it from a walled in yard to
a roof and to there to a walled in field, nevertheless he
says that all of those if something began שבת Shabbos there as
opposed to beginning in the house which is considered a distinct רשות,
reshut, but if it began שבת Shabbos in one of those spaces,
you can carry from one to the other. So it's in theory
you could get it by going through different רשות היחידs. reshut hayachid
So therefore it would be considered theoretically that you could have opened
it because you could have found it and could have gotten it
there, could have gotten the key there. But בשדה אין עירוב ועירוב
basadeh ein eruv v'eruv in the field it's not good
כרבנן k'rabbanan like the rabbis who say basically that, you know, fundamentally
that, you know, that fundamentally if you cannot, if you don't have
the key and can't get the key there, then it is not
going to count. Some take out the words כרבנן k'rabbanan because what
רבנן rabbanan are we talking about. But anyway, but that is basically
the point. So there basically are three positions. There's the position of
the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, the משנה, Mishnah, that even if the
key has no chance of being found or it's only in the
field whatever it doesn't matter, it's still good. Why? Because as גמרא
Gemara said it would be talking that, that would be according to
this answer, that would be only on יום טוב Yom Tov and
only in case of bricks, because then theoretically you could undo it.
But taking away those special cases, if it's not a case of
bricks or it's not יום טוב, Yom Tov, then the תנא קמא's
Tanna Kamma position basically would be it's completely not good, that they
only allowed it in that special case of bricks on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. And then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says actually this is
ironic because in the משנה Mishnah רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is strict,
but according to this רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is being lenient and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer actually says actually even forgetting the special case
of bricks and יום טוב, Yom Tov, it would be good if
the key is lost in the city and it would be theoretically
possible to find it and get it there. The only case it
wouldn't be good is if the key is lost in the field.
Yes, Michael.
So two questions. One is when it says נמצא המפתח, nimtza hamafteach,
what is that adding exactly?
So that's why I said, you know, I could not find really
much discussion around the נמצא. nimtza. I think the נמצא nimtza is
just is just making it clear where the key was lost. So
if it was found in the city it clearly was lost in
the city, if it was found in the field it was lost
in the field. That's how I believe. Right. Yeah, so just to
finish that.
So I'm wondering, let's say I know exactly where the key is.
Right. And but I can't get to it. Right. Does it make
a difference?
Like, yeah, then it wouldn't be any different than that you didn't
know where the key was, you know. It is funny that the
גמרא's Gemara assuming that you're allowed to say well in theory I
could have found the key and that that you know that counts.
Unless the idea of saying נמצא nimtza and again I didn't find
a discussion about this in the ראשונים Rishonim but I didn't spend
too much time looking but the little I did look, unless you
could have said an idea that it's like יש ברירה, yesh bereirah,
that because I found it on שבת Shabbos it shows that even
ערב שבת erev Shabbos it was going to be found. Right, sometimes
we say that, that based on the future it's sort of like
a certain amount of determinism, but we do say יש ברירה yesh
bereirah by rabbinic issues and this is a rabbinic issue. So you
could argue that when you find it in the city that makes
it that tells you that even on ערב שבת erev Shabbos it
was findable. But anyway, the emphasis is where was it lost. Yes.
I'm thinking of like a regular storage type of room where people
normally put it and it just one time he forgot his key.
I mean in other words is there...
Yeah, well there's no distinction between that, whether it's regular or not
regular.
Like normally he would know whether by walk, a block into the
forest or wherever it is I store this
in case whoever workmen have the place.
Yeah, so it could be that scenario but it's not limited to
that.
Whatever it is, you know.
Right, but it's not limited to that. Okay, so this answer basically
says the lenient position of the חכמים chakhamim is a very special
case of bricks on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but the general position
would be not good, why because even if it were lost in
the city the rabbis might not hold, I did not mention this,
even if in the case of lost in the city the rabbis
might not hold well you can carry it from one רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid to another because they might not agree to this position
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that they're all considered one
type of a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So the rabbis are not
impressed with the possibility of finding the key, that doesn't matter for
them, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer turns out to actually be a
lenient position as opposed to the משנה Mishnah where he sounds strict,
and he says you know what if the key was lost in
the city and you can get it by רשות היחידs reshut hayachid
that's okay.
Even on שבת. Shabbat.
Even on שבת, Shabbat, right, that's when the carrying is an issue.
So that's the answer that the basic allowance without the idea of
the key being lost in the city is this case of the
thing made out of bricks on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Yes.
But let's say you left this outside inside the city, in a
tree whatever, and it was fine בין השמשות bein hashmashes and then
you get there on שבת, Shabbos, it's eaten, it's gone.
That's no problem and we're actually going to get to that in
the next משנה. mishna. Okay, as long as it was fine בין
השמשות. bein hashmashes.
But you can say retroactively it might have been...
So we're going to discuss that, that's exactly the next
משנה. mishna. I know, so that's exactly the next משנה mishna about
if you don't know, so we'll see that in a few minutes.
Okay, so now that's answer number one. Now the גמרא Gemara goes
on and says like this.
רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו. Rabbah v’Rav Yosef d’amri tarvaihu. Now רבה
Rabbah and רב יוסף Rav Yosef say no no no, you made
that way too complicated. הכא
במגדל של עץ עסקינן. Hacha b’migdal shel etz askinan. The reason the
rabbis are lenient is not this case of bricks on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, it's your normal wood wardrobe. So why is it considered
accessible if you lost the key? דמר סבר כלי הוא ואין בנין
בכלים
ואין סתירה בכלים. D’mar savar kli hu v’ein binyan b’keilim v’ein stirah
b’keilim. Because one says a wardrobe is like a vessel, and actually
there's no problem on שבת Shabbos to build a vessel or to
destroy a vessel. It's not considered בונה. boneh. Now actually sometimes when
you when you create a vessel even if it's not other מלאכות,
melachos, it might be מכה בפטיש, makeh b’patish, but it's saying it's
not בונה. boneh. And the relevance of saying it's not בונה boneh
is that בונה boneh has its counterpart of סותר. soter. So if
you say fundamentally the concept of בונה boneh doesn't apply by a
vessel, it means you can destroy a vessel and haven't done a
מלאכה. melacha. But if the concept of בונה boneh applies, then destroying
a vessel is סותר. soter. Now it might be מקלקל, mekalkel, it
might be דרבנן, derabbanan, but anyway, so and that's why it's critical
here because the question is, can I just break the wardrobe, destroy
it, get a hatchet and destroy it? So if you say that
the concept of בונה boneh doesn't apply by vessels, then destroying doesn't
apply by vessels and it would be actually allowed. Now that might
sound crazy to you to destroy a whole wardrobe, but think about
it, when we open packages on שבת, Shabbos, we're not just concerned
about destroying a container. Now you might say that's not a full
vessel, it's only like temporary disposable, but it's a related concept. The
גמרא Gemara discusses in שבת Shabbos breaking a wine barrel to get
the wine. Okay, so this position is it's actually not a problem
to destroy a כלי. kli. Right, to destroy a כלי kli on
שבת. Shabbos. Now yes, it's considered accessible in theory you could... Now
it's actually quite funny because there's a rabbinic problem about מבטל כלי
מהיכנו. mevatel kli meiheichano. So you might think that destroying a vessel
might be a really good example of מבטל כלי מהיכנו. mevatel kli
meiheichano. But anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. So according
to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, you know why you can do
it? Because you could just take your hatchet and break into break
into the wardrobe. And that's why it's okay. ומר סבר, U’mar savar,
the other one says if it were a כלי kli I would
not disagree with you, you could break it. Like you could break
a barrel to get the wine. But here the issue is אהל
הוא. ohel hu. A wardrobe is not a vessel, it's big enough
that you know if you think about like that's a wardrobe like
a walk-in type of a big thing, right, it's actually like a
structure. It's like a house. Now it's not permanent, it's you know
transportable, but halachically it doesn't have the status of a כלי. kli.
Halachically it has the status of an אהל, ohel, of a tent,
and therefore like you know it's like a standing tent as it
were almost. It's got a roof, and roofs are very important. Yes,
but roofs are very important in הלכות שבת hilchos Shabbos because you
can't... making something with a roof is considered a type of a
בונה boneh even even if it's not a whole big house. That's
like defined as what's a classic building? It's something with a roof.
So the other opinion is it's not a vessel and therefore you
can't destroy it, and that's what the issue is and that's why
רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says if you can't find the if you
can't theoretically find the key, it's no good. So now the גמרא
Gemara says ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי. u’beflugta d’hanei tannaei. This question of what
is the status of a wardrobe is tied into the is the
same debate as the following debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתנן, Detnan, we
taught in the משנה, mishna, הקיש על גבי השידה תיבה ומגדל. hekish
al gabei hashida teiva u’migdal. So this week's פרשת תזריע מצורע, parshas
Tazria Metzora, so this is relevant, this is from מסכת זבים masechet
Zavim about a זב. Zav. A זב Zav who will make something
טמא tamei not only if he touches it but even if he
moves it. Okay? I should say again that that's not the normal
הלכה. halacha. The normal הלכה halacha is that sometimes you're טמא tamei
if you the טהור tahor person move the טמא tamei thing, if
you move a corpse even without touching it you're טמא. tamei. Here
the זב Zav is the one who is טמא, tamei, so the
direction is opposite, but the הלכה halacha is that if he goes
ahead and he let's say, you know, pushes the vessel, moves the
vessel even with an object even without touching it, he makes it
טמא. tamei. Now what happens if he comes and he's wearing gloves,
or actually he says he's wearing gloves, and he comes to this
wardrobe and he bangs on top of it and it like shakes
a little bit? Okay, has he made it טמא? tamei? Is he
considered moving it or not? So let's see what the משנה mishna
says. הקיש על גבי שידה תיבה ומגדל, Hekish al gabei shida teiva
u’migdal, he banged on this on a box or on a wardrobe,
טמאין, tmeiin, he made them טמא tamei even if he didn't touch
them. רבי נחמיה ורבי שמעון מטהרין. Rebbe Nechemia v’Rebbe Shimon metaherin. רבי
נחמיה Rebbe Nechemia and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon say it's טהור. tahor.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? mai lav be’ha
kamifligi? Isn't this what they're debating? מר סבר כלי הוא ומר סבר
אהל הוא. Mar savar kli hu u’mar savar ohel hu. One says
it's a vessel and you can make vessels טמא, tamei, and one
says it's an אהל ohel and presumably you can't make an אהל
ohel טמא. tamei. So maybe that is exactly what they are debating.
Well the גמרא Gemara is assuming, it's sort of, I'm saying, it's
sort of identifying here the idea of אוהל ohel with there's a
class, a category of כלים kelim that are considered to be so
big that they're no longer a כלי. kli. If something can contain
ארבעים סאה, arbaim se'ah, which basically means the size of a volume
of a human person. Now a normal wardrobe can't contain ארבעים סאה,
arbaim se'ah, and actually להלכה, le-halacha, if it really was that big,
it would not be able to become טמא, tameh, because it doesn't
matter that you call it an אוהל ohel or don't call it
an אוהל, ohel, it's too big of a כלי. kli. But the
גמרא Gemara is here assuming that if it had the status of
an אוהל ohel that would also take it out of כלי kli
status and not be able to be טמא. tameh. The גמרא Gemara
is going to reject it. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, ותסברא? u-tisbara? Does that really
make sense? והתניא, ve-hatanya, the ברייתא braita clarifies and it says, אוהל,
ohel, some even something that's an אוהל, ohel, assuming it's not like
banged into the ground, it's portable, ונישא, ve-nisa, if it actually was
moved by the זב, zav, טמא, tameh, it is טמא. tameh. So
yes, you can make an אוהל ohel טמא, tameh, as long as
it's not in this category of like ארבעים סאה arbaim se'ah and
so on. כלי, Kli, and the flip, if it's a vessel ואינו
נישא, ve-eino nisa, if it's not genuinely moved, טהור, tahor, it's טהור.
tahor. So the ברייתא braita makes it very clear that whether it's
an אוהל ohel or not is not relevant to this question. וקתני
סיפא, Ve-katani seifa, and we also teach at the end of that
משנה mishnah that we just quoted, ואם היו ניסוטין טמאין, ve-im hayu
nisutin tmein, that even רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that says this wardrobe is טהור tahor would agree that if
you actually moved it, it would be טמא. tameh. So we really
don't know what their debate is about. Everybody agrees if you actually
move it, it's טמא. tameh. Everybody agrees it doesn't matter if it's
כלי kli or it's an אוהל. ohel. So what's the whole issue
about the wardrobe? So the משנה mishnah goes on, says זה הכלל,
zeh ha-klal, this is the rule. נישא מחמת כוחו, nisa machmat kocho,
if something was moved because of your energy, like you pushed it
through a stick, you didn't touch it, but it was let's call
it כוחו, kocho, then טמא, tameh, it's טמא. tameh. מחמת רעדה, machmat
re'adah, if it's because of a tremor, טהור. tahor. If you bang
on the ground and that causes basically if it's your waves that
you created, not through a physical object, but you bang on the
ground and the waves caused it to shake and cause the thing
to move, that actually what? Vibrations? Vibrations, I said
wave but yes, vibrations, it's טהור, tahor, it's not moving. Okay, so
if everybody agrees to the principles, it doesn't matter if it's a
כלי kli or an
אוהל. ohel. If it actually got moved, it's טמא. tameh. Everybody agrees
that it has to be moved directly through your energy and not
through vibrations you cause. So what's the debate about this מגדל, migdal,
what are they debating? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר אביי,
ella amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says דכולי עלמא היסט מחמת כוחו
טמא, de-kulei alma hesset machmat kocho tameh, I'm going to tell you
what they're debating about. Everybody said if it moved because of your
energy, like you pushed with a stick, it's טמא. tameh. מחמת רעדה,
machmat re'adah, by
tremors, טהור, tahor, you're טהור. tahor. והכא ברעדה מחמת כוחו עסקינן. ve-hacha
be-re'adah machmat kocho askinan. It didn't move because of vibrations. All that
happened was that it vibrated. What you did is you took a
stick or you had your hand with gloves and you banged on
the box and the box shook, but it didn't actually get displaced
from its place. It just shook. How do you define I moved
it? Right? If I caused it to shake, did I move it
or not? And that's the debate. בהא
קמיפלגי, be-hai kamifligi, this is the debate. מר סבר הוי היסט, mar
savar havei hesset, that if it shakes it's considered moving, ומר סבר
לא הוי היסט, u-mar savar lo havei hesset, it's not moving. So
basically אביי Abaye says, but the point for us being, nobody debates
whether this is considered an אוהל ohel or a כלי. kli. And
the way רש"י Rashi says it is at the end of the
day, here's what would make a difference, although the גמרא Gemara doesn't
say this. If it is like this category of something that can
contain ארבעים סאה, arbaim se'ah, then everybody would agree that it's considered
to be a non-כלי kli and there would be a problem about
destroying it. If it's less than ארבעים סאה, arbaim se'ah, then everybody
would agree it is a כלי kli and there isn't a problem
destroying it. So we're back to our question, why do the חכמים
Chachamim say you have access to this? If it's small enough, the
you know, the wardrobe, the dresser, thank you, then if it's small
enough, then you should be able to break it like you can
break the barrel to get the wine. And if it's big enough,
then everybody should agree it's not good. So what is the debate
around this issue of the thing lost in the wardrobe with the
lost כלי? kli? Let's just see the גמרא's Gemara answer. So it
says
ומתניתין במאי מוקמית לה? u-matnitin be-mai mokmit lah? So therefore what's our
משנה mishnah talking
about? And what would be a case that would be debatable? So
אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, Abaye ve-Rava de-amri taro-veihu, so they say the
following: במגדול וקשור במתנא עסקינן. be-migdal u-kashur be-matna askinan. Now I'm going
to insert רש"י's Rashi point. רש"י Rashi says fine, we're talking about
a big wardrobe, like a standard wardrobe which is big, that isn't
a כלי. kli. And because it's not a כלי, kli, you can't
break it like you could break the barrel. So what's the issue
then? Why do the חכמים Chachamim think you have access to it?
Because they say basically it's like locked with a string. So you
know, we put like a metal chain around something and then attach
a lock. So what if you put a string around something and
attach a lock? Not quite as good. Okay, but anyway, but that's
what you did. And the debate is, you don't have the key,
but is it. accessible? Maybe you could just break the string. So
that's exactly the debate. ובעי סכינא למפסקה, Uve-sakinah limisekeh, but you need
a you need a knife to break the string. תנא קמא סבר
לה כרבי יוסי, Tanna kamma savar lah ke-Rabbi Yosei, the Tanna Kamma
who says it is accessible, holds like Rabbi Yosei, דאמר כל הכלים
ניטלין בשבת חוץ מן מסר הגדול ויתד של מחרישה, De-amar kol ha-kelim
nitlin be-Shabbat chutz min masar ha-gadol ve-yated shel macharishah, that you can
basically move all vessels on Shabbat except for like the big saw
and the the peg used for the plow. Basically, they're not concerned
you can use a vessel, you know, even if לצורך גופו ולצורך
מקומו. le-tzorech gufo u-le-tzorech mekomo. So go ahead, take out your knife
and cut the string. רבי אליעזר סבר לה כרבי נחמיה, Rabbi Eliezer
savar lah ke-Rabbi Nechemiah, and Rabbi Eliezer holds like Rabbi Nechemiah, דאמר
אפילו טלית ואפילו תרווד, de-amar afilu tallit ve-afilu tarvad, even a even
like a cloak, even a you know like a type of a
scooper whatever, אין ניטלין אלא לצורך תשמישן, ein nitlin ella le-tzorech tashmishan,
they can only be used for their classic use. So since you
normally don't use knives for cutting ropes, apparently it's not your hunting
knife, you would you'd be getting or it's a knife you use
in the kitchen, you're not allowed to cut it, not because cutting
it is a problem, it's a מוקצה muktzeh problem, you can't use
the knife. So it's pretty funny to say that the debate in
the משנה Mishnah is a a very special case and it all
gets back to a מוקצה muktzeh question of could you use the
knife. You know, it would have been more sense to have said
that there's somehow debating whether that's considered to be a type of
a שבירת כלי, shevirat klee, you know to cutting the rope or
something along those lines or even whether is it just the fact
about physical inaccessibility enough to create a problem. But this is the
way the גמרא Gemara makes the case. So just to review, the
גמרא Gemara assumes why is it considered accessible? Assuming it's in this
wood wardrobe and the גמרא's Gemara's answer is basically if it's not
a כלי, klee, if if it's a כלי klee small enough to
be considered a כלי, klee, then presumably everybody would agree it's accessible.
You just break it like you break, like you open packages.
Even if you don't want to break it.
Even if you don't want to, but you could the same way
you could break the wine barrel to get to the wine and
we could say open packages to get to stuff. I'm not talking
about what happens when you open them, you make it into a
כלי. klee. But if it's completely destructive, as it says, so the
way רש"י Rashi understands, we're talking that it's big, so big that
it can't be considered a כלי. klee. Therefore, you can't just break
it, that would be considered סותר. soter. But what you can do
is you can cut the rope. Then you're not breaking the actual
thing, you're just cutting the rope. And the rope isn't considered, you
know, isn't considered a מלאכה, melakhah, that's not סותר. soter. And therefore
the only question is, can you use the knife that's needed to
cut the rope, a very special case. I would just mention parenthetically
that תוספות Tosafot feels that there can be cases of סותר soter
even by כלים. kelim. And תוספות Tosafot says that this last case
is not only talking about a big thing, it's even talking about
a small thing. According to תוספות Tosafot there is a problem, although
of destroying whole כלים, kelim, so he for so that's relevant for
things like opening packages and whatnot. Yes Michael?
It's but בתמיה, bitmi, I don't understand how we're completing the two,
you know. Your packages are meant to be opened, you know, wine
casks are meant to be opened. This wardrobe isn't meant to be
destroyed.
Okay, so that's more that's along the lines of what תוספות Tosafot
says and therefore תוספות Tosafot says that even a smaller one would
be a problem, you can't destroy it, which is why the גמרא
Gemara has to be talking that the issue is about cutting the
rope. Okay, now we go on
the issue is that according to תוספות Tosafot then if it wasn't
bound with a rope then it would be a problem and that's
not what they're debating then.
Right, right. According to תוספות Tosafot if it's really a full כלי
klee and I won't go into the specifics of תוספות, Tosafot, but
along the lines you say, תוספות Tosafot might not have a problem
of opening packaging which is made to be destroyed, but something that's
a real full כלי klee according to תוספות Tosafot actually would be
סותר בכלים soter be-kelim if you would really destroy it. Right. So
let's take a look now at the next משנה Mishnah which gets
to
Rivka's case. נתגלגל חוץ לתחום, Nitgalgal chutz la-techum, so let's say before
שבת Shabbat began, the עירוב eruv rolled outside of the תחום techum
because it has to be within the תחום techum to extend your
תחום. techum. You started at point X, it was at it was
at X plus two thousand. If it rolls out so it's now
X plus two thousand and one, it started outside of your תחום,
techum, so you know you can't go ahead and build on it
and extend it. נפל עליו גל או נשרף, Nafal alav gal o
nisraf, now let's say a you know a a building fell on
it or it was burnt, או תרומה ונטמאת, o terumah ve-nitmet, it
was תרומה terumah and became טמא tamei and nobody can eat
טמא תרומה. tamei terumah. משבעוד יום, Mi-be-od yom, so by the way
Rivka a variation of נשרף nisraf would be an animal ate it.
Okay, it got
destroyed. אם משבעוד יום Im mi-be-od yom while it was still Friday,
אין עירוב, ein eruv, it's not good. משחשיכה Mi-she-chashechah if it happened
when it was dark, הרי זה עירוב. harei zeh eruv. Now then
it is the עירוב. eruv. אם ספק Im safek if you don't
know, you know maybe there were other people around and they told
you, it's hard to imagine how you wouldn't know, but let's let's
get the parameters clear. If it happened on Friday good, happened once
שבת Shabbat began no good. Let's say you don't know, which is
probably be most cases.
So there רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה אומרים, Rabbi Meir ve-Rabbi Yehudah omrim,
Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yehudah say הרי זה חמר גמל. harei zeh
chammar gamal. That is a donkey donkey driver camel leader. Of course,
which what does that mean? Which is it's a nice little idiomatic
phrase. It makes me think of, does anybody remember Dr. Dolittle and
the Pushmi-pullyu? Yeah. So that's exactly what this is, it's a Pushmi-pullyu
because apparently a donkey driver you go behind the donkey and you
drive it to go forward. A camel you hold onto the rope
and you lead the candle camel. So imagine you're standing in front
of your camel and donkey and you're trying to get them to
move. So one of them you have to like you know, one
of them or you're standing like I guess behind your, no it
would be you're standing behind your donkey and in front of your
camel, so leading your camel would pull you in this direction, you
know, getting your donkey to move would pull you in that direction.
So you're being pulled in opposite directions. And what that means is
the
following. It
means
that
if this is point A is where you start and you have,
if you didn't make an עירוב, eruv, you have 2000 אמות amot
in every direction. You made your עירוב eruv here, okay, at point
B, which should allow you to get to 4000, but what it
does is if the עירוב eruv is good, you can't go south,
right, because the whole point is it's like you started here. So
what you gain in the north direction you lose in the south.
That's classic by a normal case of an עירוב. eruv. Now you
don't know whether it worked. So if it worked you would be
allowed to travel in this area. If it didn't work you'd be
allowed to travel this area, right? So you're being pulled in opposite
directions. If it worked you can go further north, if it didn't
work you can go further south. So because you don't know, you
can't travel here and you can't travel here and you can only
travel, and you can only travel 2000 אמות amot north. You can't
go 4000 north, you can't go 2000 south. You're being pulled in
opposite directions and you can only go 2000 אמות amot north. That's
what the חכמים Chachamim say.
And then it says, that's אמר רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה. amar Rebbi
Meir veRebbi Yehuda. And then it goes on to say, רבי יוסי
ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rebbi Yossi veRebbi Shimon omrim, ספק עירוב כשר. safek
eruv kasher. This is דרבנן, derabbanan, so if there's a doubt, we'll
be lenient and we'll assume it was good. Now the גמרא Gemara
will also discuss, it's not just that it's a ספק, safek, there's
also a concept of חזקה chazakah here. That since it was good
ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, you assume when you don't know otherwise that
the status remains true even during the doubtful time. So it remained
the way you left it and you can rely on it and
it's כשר. kasher. אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rebbi Yossi, said רבי יוסי,
Rebbi Yossi, אפטולמוס העיד משום חמישה זקנים, Aftolmus he'id mishum chamisha zekenim,
אפטולמוס Aftolmus testified in the name of five זקנים, zekenim, elders, על
ספק עירוב שכשר. al safek eruv shekasher. So we have a testimony
going way back that a doubtful עירוב eruv is כשר kasher and
this case is
כשר. kasher. Let's see. Yes.
So did you really get
2004 אמות amot because if I'm קונה koneh my מקום... makom...
Fine, the גמרא Gemara is going to say this. נתגלגל חוץ לתחום,
nitgalgel chutz latchum, so if it rolled outside the תחום. tchum. And
here's exactly what Michael said and we quoted this before. אמר רבא,
amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, לא שנו אלא שנתגלגל חוץ לארבע אמות.
lo shanu ela shenitgalgel chutz le'arba amot. You know, we actually give
you an extra ארבע אמות. arba amot. So when it rolls outside
from 2000 it's not going to 2001, it would be going to
2005. Or, yeah,
אבל לתוך ארבע אמות, aval letoch arba amot, as long as it
rolled within ארבע אמות, arba amot, הנותן עירובו יש לו ארבע אמות.
hanoten eruvo yesh lo arba amot. When you put your עירוב eruv
here, it's like this is your house and like you have a
house that is ארבע אמות arba amot in each direction.
And therefore that's all considered any place within a house is all
considered to take up no halachic space. So up to ארבע אמות
arba amot it's still in the same space and therefore it is
not a problem. We quoted that before and here's where it was
originally said. Yes.
I just want to understand, you put it down, you assume it's
there, but on שבת Shabbos you walk, get there and it's not
there.
Right. So according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda who are strict, they say turn around and go home. You
can't go any further. And according to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi and
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon they say okay you don't know, but you
can assume it was fine and therefore you can keep on going.
So that's exactly, what's the הלכה? halacha? That's a good question, I
didn't check. But I believe we actually say that it's okay, but
you know what, I have to double check. Yes.
I can only do one עירוב, eruv, right? I can't like then
put another one 2000 אמות amot away from that.
Yeah, you have to start שבת Shabbos in one place.
No, even if I have two houses and you know, let's say
I have two houses and I want to be in both of
them over the course of שבת? Shabbos?
No, you can't do an עירוב eruv for half Shabbos. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, קסלקא דעתך, kasalka deitach, so now
okay, so now we get to the idea that נפלה, nafla, that
it got destroyed. We're not yet up to the ספק safek case,
just the fact that a building fell on it. קסלקא דעתך דאי
בעי בעי מצי שקיל ליה. kasalka deitach de'i ba'ei ביומא matzi shakil
lei. So we're assuming that the case would be that yes it's
got some rubble on it, but there's nothing halachically preventing you from
getting at it. You know, you move aside the rubble, it's only
stones, it's מוקצה, muktzah, but as we know דרבנן derabbanan might not
be an issue. So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי,
leima matnitin dela keRebbi, but if the משנה mishnah says that it's
considered inaccessible with stones on it, that sounds like it's against רבי,
Rebbi, because the only problem here is a דרבנן. derabbanan. it is
one of מוקצה *muktzeh*. The דאי כרבי *d’ee ke-Rabbi*, and if it
was like רבי Rebbe *Rabbi*, האמר כל דבר שהוא משום שבות לא
גזרו עליו בין השמשות *ha amar kol davar shehu mishum shevut lo
gazru alav bein hashmashot*. He wouldn’t be bothered by stones, so it’s
only rabbinic of מוקצה *muktzeh*. So why does the משנה mishna: *Mishna*
assume with stones on it it’s no good? Is it saying against
רבי *Rabbi*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, אפילו תימא כרבי
*afillu teima ke-Rabbi*, it could be going like רבי *Rabbi* and it
would have to be a דאורייתא d'oraisa. *d’Oraita* problem. So what’s the
דאורייתא d'oraisa? *d’Oraita* problem with stones on top of it? So לא
צריכא דבעי מר וחצינא *lo tzricha d’baei mar v’chatzina*, you need it
for the case
that you need, the only way you can get the stones, get
to the to the עירוב eiruv *eruv* is with like a shovel
and a hoe. Okay, you can’t just pick off stones. And therefore
it is a biblical problem. Now, what biblical problem is it, uncovering
rubble with a shovel and a hoe? So by the way, I
should tell you that a classic example about חילול שבת Shabbos, *chilul
Shabbat* for פיקוח נפש *pikuach nefesh* is a building falls on somebody.
And the discussion is, can you uncover him in order, you know,
for פיקוח נפש *pikuach nefesh*? I mean, you can uncover him and
so on. But anyway, that’s the classic scenario. So why is that
even a good example? Where’s the biblical prohibition? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says here, well, if you need a shovel, it’s biblical. Why
is it biblical? So the ריטב"א *Ritva* and other ראשונים *Rishonim* say
that then it would be considered to be, you know, you can’t
do basically types of changing of the landscape. If you change the
landscape in like in a house, it could be a type of
בונה *boneh* because now, you know, you’ve improved the floor of your
house or you’ve improved your front yard. You know, if you change
the landscape out in a field, it could be a חורש *choresh*,
it’s preparing the ground for planting. Now, there could be a lot
of scenarios like, you know, it’s not your field, you know, you
don’t care whether it’s prepared, maybe it’s not even a field that’s
fit for planting, but that’s what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming
at least that some of those cases could fall into the ambit
of a real מלאכה *melacha* and that’s why it would be an
issue. וצריכא *v’tzricha*, and you need to tell me all the scenarios
in the משנה mishna *Mishna*. דאי תנא נתגלגל *d’ei tana nitgalgel*, if
it had just said rolling out,
I would say, okay, that I understand that that’s no good משום
דליתי גביה *mishum d’leitey gabei*, it’s no longer by you, it’s not
even accessible. אבל נפל עליו גל *aval nafal alav gal*, but if
rubble is on it, דאיתיה גביה *d’eiteih gabei*, okay, it’s right next
to me, it’s in the same space, I just can’t get to
it. אימא ליהוי עירוב *eima leihavei eruv*, maybe that would be good.
That maybe that was also like the idea, you know, possibly was
discussed before about being in the wardrobe. It’s right there, I just
can’t get to it, maybe that would be good. ואי תנא נפל
עליו גל *v’ei tana nafal alav gal*, if it just had that
case and said that that was no good, משום דמיכסי *mishum d’michasi*,
that’s because it’s not visible and it’s covered, so it really is
like it no longer exists. אבל נתגלגל *aval nitgalgel*, but if it
rolled, so you see it, I see it, it’s right there. זימנין
דאתי זיקא ומייתי ליה *zimnin d’ati zika u’maiti leh*, not only that,
sometimes a wind can come and blow it back. So maybe that
should be good. So הוה אמינא ליהוי עירוב *hava amina leihavei eruv*,
maybe it would be good. צריכא *tzricha*. So not that there’s a
huge הוה אמינא *hava amina* in either of these directions, but it’s
just trying to explain why we gave a couple of scenarios. So
you should understand that however it is inaccessible, doesn’t matter, and it
is not an עירוב *eruv*. Okay, now או נשרף תרומה terumah ונטמאת
*o nisraf terumah v’nitmet*, oh, נשרף *nisraf*, or it was burned and
תרומה *terumah* became טמאה *temeiah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says why
do you need those scenarios? למה לי *lama li*? So why do
you need that? תנא נשרף להודיע כוחו דרבי יוסי *tana nisraf l’hodia
kocho d’Rabbi Yossi*, top of ל"ה עמוד ב' *lamed hey amud beis*,
it tells נשרף *nisraf* to tell me the power of רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yossi *Rabbi Yossi*’s position. What’s the power of רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yossi *Rabbi Yossi*’s position? Meaning that רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi *Rabbi Yossi*
who says that if it’s a ספק safek *safek* you could assume
it’s good, is even in an extreme case where it got completely
destroyed. You know, so you might say if it’s still here, I
could assume it was here in the right way when שבת Shabbos
*Shabbat* begins. No, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yossi* would say you
can assume it’s good even if it’s being completely destroyed. תנא תרומה
ונטמאת *tana terumah v’nitmet* and תרומה *terumah* is perhaps the least changed.
It’s physically here, it’s in front of you, you can touch it,
it’s just that its halakhic status changed. So that case you might
say more people should agree, you know, there should be more consensus
that that you can assume remained okay. So no, that’s להודיע כוחו
דרבי מאיר *l’hodia kocho d’Rabbi Meir* to tell you that when רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says no good, it’s even in that
case. So why do we give all these cases? To
tell you the position that רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi*, that it’s good
if there’s a ספק safek *safek*, you can assume it’s good, is
even if now it’s completely destroyed. And the position of רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir* that says if it’s a ספק safek *safek*
you have to assume it, you’re in this doubtful case and it’s
the, you know, the worst of both scenarios, you have to live
with the ספק safek. *safek*, is even in a case when it’s
physically present and the only question is whether its halakhic status changed.
Okay, and now we’re going to get on to the core of
the משנה mishna *Mishna* which is this debate of when you have
the doubt, can you assume like רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi* that it
was good and keep on going 4,000 to the north, or do
you have to assume like רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* that
you don’t know if it was good or not and therefore you
can only go 2,000 to the south? You can’t go beyond the
עירוב *eruv* and you also can’t go to, I mean only 2,000
to the north. You can’t go beyond the עירוב *eruv* and you
can’t go in the opposite direction either.
If he’s burnt it, it’s actually in an edible state. I mean,
it’s תרומה *terumah* טמאה *temeiah*, it can be burned, you can still
get הנאה *hana’ah* from it, right?
Yeah, but it’s not edible. It has to be ראוי לאכילה *ra’ui
l’achila*.
So okay, so in case of a גל *gal*, then we’re not
talking about... You're right.
You could have—yeah, you could have said that, that so much fell
on it that it's not edible. That's a good point. You could
have said that. Okay, so now let's see. Now let's get to
this issue of this debate of what we have to deal with
in the case of ספק. safek So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: וסבר רבי מאיר ספיקא לחומרא? u'savar Rebbi Meir sfeka l'chumra? Does
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir. really say that if you have a doubt
you have to be strict, especially as we're going to see, the
question is that this is only rabbinic? So there we should maybe
be lenient in a case of doubt. דהתנן, d'hatnan, we taught in
the משנה: mishna טמא שירד לטבול, tamei sheyarad litvol, somebody טמא tamei
went to go to the מקוה. mikvah. ספק טבל ספק לא טבל,
safek taval safek lo taval, he's not sure if he went to
the מקוה mikvah or not. You know, he doesn't remember, you know,
yeah, that happens to me sometimes. I don't even know what I
was doing the last hour. Anyway, okay. ואפילו טבל, v'afilu taval, maybe
it means he had a ספק—even if he knows he dunked in
the מקוה, mikvah, ספק טבל בארבעים סאה ספק לא טבל בארבעים סאה,
safek taval b'arba'im sa safek lo taval b'arba'im sa, he's not sure
the מקוה mikvah was full, it had ארבעים סאה arba'im sa in
it, it was kosher. Or, וכן שתי מקואות, v'chein shtei mikvaos, let's
say there were שתי מקואות, shtei mikvaos, באחת יש בה ארבעים סאה
ובאחת אין בה ארבעים סאה, b'achas yesh bah arba'im sa u'v'achas ein
bah arba'im sa, one you know was kosher and one isn't kosher,
וטבל באחת מהן ואינו יודע באיזו מהן טבל, v'taval b'achas mehen v'eino
yodeia b'eizo mehen taval, and you went into one of them
and you don't know which one you went into. So all these
cases, you don't know if you became טהור tahor now or not,
so the הלכה halacha is ספיקו טמא. sfeko tamei. You have to
assume that you're טמא, tamei, which makes sense: you were טמא tamei
before and you don't know if you became טהור, tahor, so you
assume to remain טמא. tamei. במה דברים אמורים, bamei devarim amurim, when
is this true? בטומאה חמורה, b'tumah chamurah, when it's a strict טומאה,
tumah, meaning a biblical טומאה. tumah. אבל בטומאה קלה, aval b'tumah kalah,
if it's a—if it's a light one, meaning a rabbinic טומאה, tumah,
כגון, k'gon, and now what are examples of this? This is from
the list of the eighteen things of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and
בית הלל. Beis Hillel. שאכל אוכלין טמאים, she'achal ochlin tmeiyim, you ate
טמא tamei food. Food normally can't—טמא tamei food cannot מטמא metamei a
person, but if you eat it, the Rabbis said you could become
טמא. tamei. Or similarly, ושתה משקין טמאים, v'shasa mashkin tmeiyim, you drank
טמא tamei liquids. So again, touching them would not make you טמא,
tamei, but rabbinically drinking it makes you טמא. tamei. ובא ראשו ורובו
במים שאובין, u'va rosho v'rubo b'mayim shu'uvin, or if you basically immersed
yourself in drawn water. That was a rabbinic טומאה tumah because they
didn't want people basically bathing after the מקוה mikvah and saying that
it was the bathing that made them טהור. tahor. או שנפלו על
ראשו ורובו שלשה לוגין מים שאובין, o shenafelu al rosho v'rubo shlosha
login mayim shu'uvin, a similar issue about taking a shower. They didn't
want them doing it right after going to the מקוה. mikvah. So
if you did, and if drawn
water, שלשה לוגין shlosha login of—of drawn water fell on your head,
you showered with it essentially, then you're also טמא. tamei. All of
those are pure rabbinic טומאות. tumos. So if that was your טומאה,
tumah, in that case, וירד לטבול, v'yarad litvol, and you went down
to go to the מקוה, mikvah, ספק טבל ספק לא טבל, safek
taval safek lo taval, you didn't know if you went, ואפילו טבל,
v'afilu taval, even if you definitely dunked, ספק טבל בארבעים סאה ספק
לא טבל בארבעים סאה, safek taval b'arba'im sa safek lo taval b'arba'im
sa, you don't know if the מקוה mikvah had ארבעים סאה arba'im
sa in it or not, or וכן שתי מקואות, v'chein shtei mikvaos,
or if there were שתי מקואות, shtei mikvaos, באחת יש בה ארבעים
סאה ובאחת אין בה ארבעים סאה, b'achas yesh bah arba'im sa u'v'achas
ein bah arba'im sa, one had and one—one had ארבעים סאה, arba'im
sa, one didn't, one was kosher, one wasn't, וטבל באחת מהן ואינו
יודע באיזו מהן טבל, v'taval b'achas mehen v'eino yodeia b'eizo mehen taval,
you went into one of them and you don't know which one,
ספיקו טהור. sfeko tahor. Doubt—therefore, by the doubt you're טהור. tahor. The
upshot of all of this is that by a rabbinic טומאה tumah
we say your ספק you're טהור, tahor, and we assume a סתם
משנה stam mishna is רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir And this case is
even more strict than the משנה mishna because this case you knew
you began being טמא. tamei. And even though your original status was
טמא, tamei, we assume if it's a ספק we'll be lenient. So
certainly in our משנה mishna we should assume when you put it
there in a good way before שבת, Shabbos why is it רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir similarly lenient? That's the גמרא's Gemara question. By the
way, this משנה mishna ends, רבי יוסי מטמא. Rebbi Yossi metamei. רבי
יוסי says in that מקוה mikvah case you are טמא. tamei. So
רבי יוסי also seems a contradiction: he's lenient in our משנה mishna
and in this case of doubt he's strict. So we'll worry about
רבי יוסי in a minute, but now we're going to focus on
רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir How come רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is strict
in our משנה mishna, and lenient by the
טומאה? tumah?
Why do you assume there's a contradiction? One's talking about טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah and one's talking about מבוי. mavo.
So that's always an answer. Maybe there's reasons why טומאה וטהרה tumah
v'taharah is more lenient, and it's worth mentioning that there's a general
principle that ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים טהור. safek tumah b'reshus harabbim tahor.
And that might be more than normally other cases. That might be
a special idea that we are particularly lenient in a רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim and if you assume that's the scenario, you know, maybe
that's what's going on. So you're absolutely right, the גמרא Gemara could
have answered that, could have said טומאה tumah is different, you know,
because it has special rules that allow for more leniency. The גמרא
Gemara will make a difference but by emphasizing the difference of תחומין,
techumin, not the difference of טומאה. tumah. But you're right that, you
know, given rules of ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים, safek tumah b'reshus harabbim,
it's interesting the גמרא Gemara did not go there. So let's see
what the גמרא's Gemara's answer is. קסבר רבי מאיר, kasavar Rebbi Meir,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is of the opinion תחומין דאורייתא נינהו. techumin
d'oraisa ninhu. תחומין techumin are biblical. The reason רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is strict in our משנה Mishnah, is if it were rabbinic he'd
be lenient, but he's strict in our משנה Mishnah, because he feels
a תחום techum is דאורייתא. De'oraisa So the גמרא Gemara
says, וסבר רבי מאיר תחומין דאורייתא? v'savar Rebbi Meir techumin d'oraisa? Does
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir really hold תחומין techumin are דאורייתא? De'oraisa והתנן,
vehatnan, we taught in the
משנה, Mishnah, אם אין יכול לבלעו בזו, im ein yachol l'avli'o b'zo,
if you can't swallow it, I'll tell you what that means in
a
minute, בזו אמר רבי דוסתאי בר ינאי משום רבי מאיר, b'zo amar
Rebbi Dostai bar Yannai mishum Rebbi Meir, in this case אמר רבי
דוסתאי בר ינאי
משום רבי מאיר
amar Rebbi Dostai bar
Yannai
mishum Rebbi Meir שמעתי שמקילין. shamati she'makkilin. So if you measure it
as the bird
flies.
Okay, so here you are and here's your
mountain. So basically you measure it straight through the mountain as the
bird flies. Now, they would... how would you measure straight through the
mountain, right? I mean, how do you do that? How do you
measure that? So the הלכה *halakha* is that you use, for whatever
reason this is הלכה *halakha*, 50 אמה *amah* measuring strings, okay? So
if the mountain is less than 50 אמות *amot* wide, you know,
whatever, 49 אמות *amot*, so you can do it. Every... you just
move aside, one person stands here, one person stands here, right? And
you have your 50 אמה *amah* string, and then you move back
up here and you mark where your 50 אמה *amah* string ended
and you continue going straight. So that's called יכול להבליעו *yachol le-havli'o*,
you can swallow the hill with your 50 אמה *amah* string. So
by moving aside and doing the measuring and moving back, you've measured
your 50 אמה *amah*.
And then you can hike up the whole mountain back and continue...
yes, and then when you're walking on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* you can
do this, because you do it as again as the bird flies,
which by the way, it makes it so much easier to פסקן
*pasken* הלכות halachos *halakhot* of עירובין *Eruvin*. You just look at a
map and you measure, you don't have to worry about the topography.
Okay? Now, what is this אינו יכול להבליעו *eino yachol le-havli'o*? What
if this was 100 אמות *amot*? So there is... you can't swallow
it. Now, you could say like who cares if you can't swallow
it? Just do multiple strings and you mark this and then you
continue. For whatever reason, the הלכה *halakha* is that if you can't
swallow it, then we might have to go like measure by going
up and down the mountain and so on. Now, how do you...
but even when you do that, the idea of מקדרין בהרים *mekadrin
beharim*, again, it's very strange why the... let's just acknowledge there are
alternative ways of doing this. Okay? But anyway, מקדרין בהרים *mekadrin beharim*
means you're going to walk up and down the mountain to measure,
but you're still going to try to be measuring the horizontal. And
how would you do that? One... you use a four אמה *amah*
string. One person stands here, the other person stands here, okay? And
this guy holds the string by his chest and you hold it
by... this guy holds it by his feet. So if it's, you
know, based on the slope, you're going to get a measurement and
you continue that all the way up. So you're going to get
a measurement that is more... that is more horizontal. It's not completely
the slope. Depending on the slope, it might be mostly horizontal or
it might be a lot of vertical in there. And you do
that multiple times in order to measure the distance if this is
more than 50 אמות *amot*. Okay? Why you have to do it
that way, I don't know. Why not use a bigger string? I
don't know. But that's the הלכה *halakha*. Okay? So that's what we're
talking about. So let's see how this is relevant for our issue
right now.
Okay, so רבי *Rabbi*... so if you cannot swallow it in the
50 אמה *amah* string, so then in the name of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* we say you try to pierce through the
mountain. Okay, which means you do this other way where you basically
you still try to do it as the bird flies, but in
a more complicated way. Now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, why is
that a problem? ואי סלקא דעתך *ve-i salka daitakh* תחומין דאורייתא Tchumin
De'oraisa *tchumin de-Oraita*, because if you think תחומין Tchumin, *tchumin* are biblical,
מי מקדרין *mi mekadrin*? We would not allow piercing the mountain for
biblical measurements. How do you know that? ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה *ve-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Abbuha*, רב נחמן *Rav
Nachman* says in the name of רבה בר אבוה *Rabba bar Abbuha*,
אין מקדרין *ein mekadrin*, you do not pierce through mountains, לא בערי
מקלט *lo be-arei miklat*, not by cities of refuge, because cities of
refuge would have the area directly around them would also be קולט
*kolat*. So even if you didn't get into the city gates, even
if you were just in the immediate sort of like, you know,
buffer zone, it would also absorb
you. And to measure, you know, and basically the 2000 אמות *amot*
outside the city, so to measure the 2000 אמות *amot* outside the
city, you do not go as the bird flies. You would actually
have to measure the actual way in which it would take you
to walk, the actual... so you get a lot less distance if
it's hilly, right? Or if it's, you know, if it's not flat.
Okay, so there you do not measure as the bird flies. ולא
בעגלה ערופה *ve-lo be-eglah arufah*. By עגלה ערופה *eglah arufah* you measure
which is the closest city and you do not do it as
the bird flies, you do it as it actually would take you
to walk on the ground. So what's the principle? The גמרא Gemara's
*Gemara* says it seems that the principle is that for biblical הלכות
*halakhot* we actually go by as the dog walks, not as the
bird flies. So how could it be that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* says by תחומין Tchumin *tchumin* you go as the bird
flies? It must be that תחומין Tchumin *tchumin* is rabbinic. So we've
got this problem, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* it seems if
he allows as the bird flies, must be saying that it's rabbinic.
So the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* accepts
that argument, it assumes that, you know, the principle of one applies
to the other and if it's true for ערי מקלט *arei miklat*
and true for עגלה ערופה *eglah arufah*, it would be true for
תחומין Tchumin *tchumin* if it were biblical. And because the משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah* ends by
saying. Whatever the quote ends by saying, מפני שהן של תורה, the
reason you do not do it as the bird flies is because
they are biblical. So if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir allows as the
bird flies, it must be that it is rabbinic. So the גמרא
Gemara. says no, I'll get out of it, לא קשיא, lo kashya,
it's not difficult, הא דידיה הא דרביה, ha didei ha derabbeih, one
is his, one is his רבי'ס, Rebbe's, meaning when רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says in the משנה, Mishnah, right, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
strict in the משנה, Mishnah I'm sorry, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
strict in the משנה, Mishnah what does the משנה Mishnah say? It
says, right, I'm sorry, he's strict in the משנה, Mishnah, but in
this case of, where were we, one minute, excuse
me, שמעתי שמקדין
בהרים,
shamati
shemakdin beharim, right, thank you.
The case where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, yes, thank you, so
where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you do as the bird flies,
which we're trying to prove means that he thinks it's rabbinic, that
was not in his own name. דייקא נמי, deika nami, and that
also is inferred from the language, תני, tani, because it says there
by 'as the bird flies', בזו אמר רב דוסטאי ברבי ינאי משום
רבי מאיר. bezo amar Rav Dostai bar Yannai mishum Rabbi Meir. So
רב דוסטאי Rav Dostai said in the name of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir that what did רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. say? רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir said שמעתי שמקדין בהרים, shamati shemakdin beharim, I heard, I have
a tradition, it's not necessarily my own opinion. So you see that
you don't have to lock him into that position. שמע מינה, shma
mina, that's a good position. So meaning, how has the גמרא Gemara
reconciled this? Right now we have רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, strict in
our משנה Mishnah by תחומין, lenient by טומאה. Tumah. If anything,
well, first of all, you have the answer that maybe lenient by
טומאה Tumah because ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים. safek tumah birshut harabim. But
bracketing that, if anything, you should be more strict by טומאה Tumah
because the guy started as being טמא. tamei. Why are you strict
in the משנה Mishnah? and lenient by טומאה? Tumah? And the answer
is, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds that תחומין are דאורייתא De'oraisa. and
that's why he is strict. And we are strict by טומאה Tumah
when it's דאורייתא De'oraisa. as well. How about this idea of measuring
as the bird flies, which you only do by דרבננס? Derabbanans? No,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir actually, he's only quoting his רבי who says
you measure as the bird flies.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learned the...
right. Well, that's a good point. Anyway, so according to whatever tradition
he heard, you do as the bird flies, but רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir personally holds תחומין דאורייתא De'oraisa and would not measure as the
bird flies. That's the גמרא's Gemara way of dealing with רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. But now we're not done. רמי, rami, he challenges רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir דאורייתא אדאורייתא. De'oraisa a-De'oraisa. We'll show to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir I'll show you that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is not
consistent even in דאורייתא'ס. De'oraisa's. You're trying to say רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says we're strict by דאורייתא'ס, De'oraisa's, that would be the טומאה
Tumah case if it's biblical, that would be the משנה mishnah, if
תחומין are דאורייתא. d'oraita I'm going to show you he's not consistent
even by דאורייתא. d'oraisa,
דתנן, detnan, we learn in the משנה, mishnah נגע באחד בלילה, naga
be'echad balaila, somebody touched a person at night. Okay, you went and
you touched a person or put your hand on the person, ואינו
יודע אם חי אם מת, ve'eino yodeia im chai im meit, and
you don't know that he was necessarily living at that time. It
was a sick person, they were at, you know, their last stage
of life, you touched them, ולמחר השכים ומצאו מת, ulemachar hishkim umetzau
meit, and in the morning you saw that he had passed away
sometime in the night. Who knows what you did, but in the
morning you saw he had passed away sometime in the night. And
you don't know if you touched him before or after he passed
away. Are you טמא tamei or not? So רבי מאיר מטהר, Rabbi
Meir metaher, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're טהור. tahor. וחכמים מטמאי,
vachachamim metam'ei, and the חכמים Chachamim say you're טמא. tamei. Why? שכל
טומאות כשעת מציאתן. shekol tumot kesha'at metziatan. We have a rule by
טומאה, Tumah, which is you go by what the current state is.
If right now the thing is טמא, tamei, then you assume that
when you touched it, it was טמא. tamei. You have to take
the current status of טומאה Tumah and assume backwards. So that's the
חכמים's Chachamim's position. But we're interested in רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is lenient by טומאה Tumah and this is a
דאורייתא d'oraisa case. So why is he strict by טומאה Tumah in
the מקוה Mikvah case and lenient by טומאה Tumah in the touching
case? So there's an obvious answer we will see. אמר רבי ירמיה,
amar Rabbi Yirmiyah, so רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah said, משנתנו שהיה עליה
השרץ בין השמשות. mishnateinu shehaya aleha hasheretz bein hashemashot. You're right. Maybe
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir sometimes is lenient by דאורייתא'ס, De'oraisa's, but our
case in the משנה mishnah: where he's being strict by תחומין is
that it wasn't really a ספק. That the dead rodent was on
the תרומה the entire period of שבת coming in. And that's why
he's strict. Of course, if that's true, why would anybody be lenient?
So the גמרא says it's not a ספק anymore, you said it
was on it the whole time. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's
true, said the גמרא, בהא לימא רבי יוסי ספק עירוב כשר? beha
leima Rabbi Yossi safek eiruv kasher? So how could רבי יוסי therefore
say it's כשר? kasher? You can't say that. We've still got a
problem. Okay, it can't be that it was definite. So רבא ורב
יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Rava veRav Yosef de'amri tarveihu, so רבא Rava and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef say, no, no, here's the case. Maybe רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir sometimes is lenient even by דאורייתא'ס. De'oraisa's. Why is
he strict in the משנה? mishnah, Here's the case. הכא
בשתי כיתי עדים עסקינן. hacha bishtei kitei eidim askinan. We're dealing with
two contradictory witnesses. אחת אומרת, achat omeret, one set of witnesses say,
אחת אומרת מבעוד יום נטמא, achat omeret mibe'od yom nitma, it got...
it was טמא tamei before שבת began. ואחת אומרת, ve'achat omeret, and
the other said משהחשכה, mishechashecha, and that it was... it was when
it was dark. So what's the גמרא's basic answer? The גמרא's answer
is like this. When you have... Here's how the גמרא lines up
the cases. There are three cases in the גמרא. There's the case
of not knowing whether the מקווה mikveh was כשר, kosher, and there
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says by דאורייתא d'oraisa we're strict. There it's
easy to understand why we're strict if you don't know because the
status you began with was that you began being טמא. tamei. Okay,
so that's easy, you can keep your current status. But in our
משנה, mishnah. it began being okay. Similar to the guy in the
bed, he began being alive. Okay, so those are two, those are
comparable. Forget the טומאה tumah case, that's not relevant. That's when it
started being bad. But in our משנה and the guy in bed,
those both started in being in the good state. And in one,
the תחומים techumim case, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you have to
assume the worst, and in the guy with the guy who's dying
sometime in the middle of the night, רבי מאיר says you can
be lenient. So that's the question how to deal with those two
cases. So the גמרא's answer is, here's what undermined the fact that
you knew it started good in the case of our משנה: that
there's actually witnesses that said it was bad. Now, if it was
just witnesses there wouldn't be a debate, so they're contradictory witnesses. But
the fact that there exists one set of witnesses that says it
was bad, that undermines the חזקה, chazakah, undermines the fact that you
knew it started good. So now we have three scenarios. If it
started bad and it's a דאורייתא, de-oraisa, you have to assume it
remained bad. If it started good and even in a דאורייתא like
the guy in bed, you could assume it remained good. But if
it started good like the case of תחומים, techumim, but a special
case that there are witnesses that said it was no good, even
if it's contradictory witnesses, that undermines the status and therefore it's no
good. Like the חכמים. Chachamim. The other guy. Right, that's what רבי
מאיר's position would be. Okay, so that's pretty complicated. Let's see another
answer to this. רבא אמר, Rava amar, we'll just read a little
bit more, top of ל"ו עמוד א'. lamed vav amud aleph. רבא
Rava says, התם תרי חזקי לקולא והכא חדא חזקה לקולא. hasham trei
chazakei lekula ve-acha chada chazaka lekula.
No,
no, no, no, no. Here it's easy. It's two versus one. In
our משנה, you have one חזקה chazaka of a good status, that
the food was where it needed to be before שבת began. Okay,
but it's a דאורייתא and then you don't know what happened. Can
you assume it retained that status or not? רבי מאיר is strict.
Okay, you don't allow the חזקה chazaka to override the fact that
now you know it's not good. Why is he lenient by touching
the dead person who winds up dead? He says you have two
חזקות. chazakas. A, the guy started being alive before night, and B,
what's your other חזקה? chazaka?
You started being טהור. tahor. So when you have two חזקות, chazakas,
then you can, then you can rely on it. But with only
one you cannot. By the way, the רבנן Rabbanan disagree though. The
רבנן Rabbanan disagree. Now by the way, this is, this is a
classic question in הלכות of dealing with doubt, which is: we normally
have a principle you go by חזקה, chazaka, status quo, and we
assume the status quo remains. But what if you know that at
a certain point it stopped? It's a חזקה chazaka versus, you know,
like, like here it was already איתרע חזקה, itra chazaka, you know,
there was a, like a חזקה דהשתא. chazaka d'hashtah. You have a
current state, you had a חזקה דמעיקרא, chazaka d'meikara, the past state
that you know, and you have a חזקה דהשתא, chazaka d'hashtah, you
have the current state, and they're competing. Do you assume, you know,
the good state remained, or do you assume the bad state, you
know, started earlier? So רבי מאיר would normally say I'd normally be
lenient. I, no, excuse me, I normally would be strict actually. That's
the case of our משנה. You don't know if the עירוב remained
there or didn't remain there, and now it's no good, and again
the גמרא is assuming it's דאורייתא, so רבי מאיר says I'm going
to be strict. But if you have a double חזקה, chazaka, if
not only was the guy alive but you were טהור, tahor, there
רבי מאיר says that you can be lenient, and there and we'll
continue with that tomorrow. I just have to tell you this idea
of, oh my god, two חזקות chazakas reminds me of this joke
that there was this actuary that would never go fly on a
plane because he had figured out the odds of somebody carrying a
bomb on a plane and he was always like so anxious and
he was miserable and like even if he would have to fly,
you know, he would be sweating the whole time. Then once he
was traveling with his friend and he was like cool as a
cucumber, totally calm, and his friend said what happened? How, why are
you so calm? He says ha, he says this time I brought
a bomb on the plane. Think about the odds of there being
two bombs. So
anyway, alright.